Guide to the J. Walter Thompson Company. Albert B. Stridsberg Papers, 1950-2001 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company. Albert B. Stridsberg papers 1950-2001 and undated
J. Walter Thompson Company.
5.7 linear feet Extent: 3,111 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.00750
Language: English.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
However, original audiovisual materials are closed to research until use copies can be produced.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Albert B. Stridsberg Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a transfer in 2000-2001.
Biographical Note
Albert Stridsberg worked at the J. Walter Thompson Company in the United States and abroad from 1960-1967 and 1969-1972 as an account representative, internal corporate consultant, and assistant to E. G. Wilson. He later taught advertising at Marist College in Poughkeepsie, NY.
Collection Overview
Correspondence, memos, reports, speeches, and printed items relating to Stridsberg's career at the J. Walter Thompson Company. Documentation includes reports and pamphlets that address television advertising to men and children, brand advertising, public service campaigns, the role of research in advertising, tobacco marketing, JWT's international offices and clients. Also included are texts of speeches by Rena Bartos and other JWT officers, and Stridsberg's reminiscences of his years at J. Walter Thompson Company in the 1960s and 1970s, especially regarding Ralph Nader and the Ford Motor Company as well as international cigarette marketing. The printed material includes issues of a serial, Motivations (1956-1957), and other bulletins published by Ernest Dichter's Institute for Motivational Research. Audiovisual materials include radio compilation cassettes produced by the Radio Advertising Bureau and other entities; 16mm films Coca-Cola campaigns by McCann-Erickson agency (undated) and a 1976 reel from Dancer Fitzgerald Sample. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
Subject Headings
Stridsberg, Albert B.; Bartos, Rena; Nader, Ralph; Ford Motor Company; Ernest Dichter International, Institut fèur Motiv- und Marketingforschung; J. Walter Thompson Company; Coca-Cola Company; McCann-Erickson Worldwide; Radio Advertising Bureau; Advertising agencies; Advertising agencies -- United States; Advertising, Public service; Advertising -- Research; Brand name products; Marketing; Motivation research (Marketing); Radio advertising; Television advertising; Tobacco -- Marketing; Audiocassettes; Speeches; Motion pictures; T-shirt; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History
Contents of Collection
- General Files, 1950-2001 and undated
  - Advertising agencies expanding their scope and inproving profits (by Joan Merlis, Salomon Brothers), 1987 (Box 1)
  - Advertising history collections pamphlets, undated (Box 1)
  - Advertising Research Foundation: Motivation research, 1957 (Box 1)
  - Addvertising Self-Regulation: A Global Perspective (with James Neelankavil), 1980 (Box 1)
  - Cereals in India, 1962 (Box 1)
  - Children's television programming and advertising, 1972, 1977 (Box 1)
  - Cigarette marketing, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Computer applications, 1969-1977 (Box 1)
  - Consolidated marketing recommendations for soup, Benelux countries (McCann-Erickson), 1960 (Box 1)
  - Consumerism, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Controversy Advertising: How Advertisers Present Point of View in Public Affairs (not attributed but written by Stridsberg), 1977 (Box 2)
  - Devine project, 1969 (Box 2)
  - Dillon Agnew & Martin, analysis of business potential, 1969 (Box 2)
  - Effective Advertising Self-Regulation, 1974 (Box 2)
  - Establishing Accountability, circa 1989 (Box 2)
  - European consumers (including The Consumer's Food-Buying Habits and Les Commerces de détail en Europe Occidentale), 1954-1958 (Box 2)
  - Florida conference, 1969 (Box 2)
  - Glen Souham article, 1986 (Box 2)
  - Global brands, 1973-1992 (Box 2)
  - Global vision with a local touch (Grey), 1984 (Box 2)
  - Government regulation and control in the marketplace, 1968 (Box 2)
  - Government regulation position paper, drafts, undated (Box 2)
  - How brand advertising benefits an economy, 1986 (Box 2)
  - How to move minds (public service campaigns), 1970 (Box 2)
  - Improvement of information retrieval, 1970 (Box 2)
  - Indonesia market report, 1973 (Box 3)
  - Information plan, 1973, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Institute for Motivational Research, 1956-1957 (Box 3)
  - International Nestlé survey, 1965, (3 folders) (Box 3)
  - International marketing, 1972 (Box 3)
  - International marketing: Foreign Trade and Investment Act, 1961-1975 (Box 3)
  - International marketing: Nabisco, 1966-1972 (Box 4)
  - International marketing approaches: Cosmetics in Japan and U.S., 1981 (Box 4)
  - JWT historical project, 1977 (Box 4)
  - JWT/Unilever around the world, 1972 (Box 4)
  - JWT world highlights, 1973 (Box 4)
  - Letters from Stridsberg, recollections of JWT activities in the 1960s, 2000-2001 (Box 4)
  - Lisbon operation, 1958 (Box 4)
  - Makro Atacadista (Brazil), 1972 (Box 4)
  - Marketing and Distribution of Tobacco (UN study), 1978 (Box 4)
  - Marketing research, miscellaneous reports, 1966-1987 (Box 4)
  - Marketing Review: Nutricia Koffiemelk Brands (Netherlands), 1962 (Box 4)
  - Material relating to William Souhami and Glenn Souhami, 1986-1996 (Box 5)
  - Media Research Index, 1950-1977 (Box 5)
  - Memorandum re evaluation program, 1966 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous, 1958-1989 (Box 5)
  - Motivation research, 1955 (Box 5)
  - Motivations, 1956-1957 (Box 5)
  - Myths, Men and Beer: An Analysis of Beer Commercials, 1987 (Box 5)
  - NAD Casase Report: Voluntary Self-Regulation, 1992 (Box 5)
  - New business, 1964-1965, (3 folders) (Box 5)
  - Operation of Lux Toilet Soap Film Star Co-ordinating Unit--London, 1965 (Box 6)
  - Oral history, JWT, 1977 (Box 6)
  - Outline of Kraft/JWT international advertising centralized supervision, 1973 (Box 6)
  - Portugal--Lisbon; Basilio Fernandes (Basil Fernandes), 1954-1955, (2 folders) (Box 6)
  - Principles of operation, international offices, 1972 and undated (Box 6)
  - Product life cycle speech, 1977 (Box 6)
  - Qualitative research (Rena Bartos)/The Art of Asking Why (Paul Lazarsfeld), 1986 (Box 6)
  - Report on advertising agencies in the Far East, 1964 (Box 6)
  - Report on development of JWT London financial advertising, 1965 (Box 6)
  - Report on diversification, for Imperial Tobacco (London Office), 1966 (Box 6)
  - Report on Institute of Marketing and Sales Management student conference (London), 1964 (Box 6)
  - Reports on advertising and children, 1978-1985 (Box 6)
  - Research, Creativity, and Tunnel Vision, 1973 (Box 7)
  - Seymour presentation, Enjay Chemical, 1970 (Box 7)
  - Seymour (Dan)/Bart Cummings discussion, AAAA Conference, 1969 (Box 7)
  - Simple Complexities of Marketing in America (Henry Schachte), 1967 (Box 7)
  - Target Plan (T-Plan), 1973 (Box 7)
  - Television Today, Television Tomorrow (JWT Europe), 1983 (Box 7)
  - Thailand and Southeast Asia: Examination of Company opportunities, 1969 (Box 7)
  - The Potential of Thoroughbred Breeding as a Business Proposition, 1970 (Box 7)
  - The Rise of the Tinkerers (on government regulation of advertising), undated (Box 7)
  - Tobacco advertising survey, 1987 (Box 7)
  - Unilever plan for good advertising, 1964 (Box 7)
  - U.S. Tele-Service Corp., catalog of monitored commercials, 1960 (Box 7)
  - Value added taxes, 1972 (Box 7)
  - Who Needs Advertising in an Affluent Society? (Norman Strouse), 1967 (Box 7)
  - Working women as a target audience, 1973 (Box 7)
  - Working Women: The Moving Target (by Rena Bartos), 1974-1976, (2 folders) (Box 7)
- Board Game
  - The New Product Development Game (Case & McGrath, Inc.), 1975 (Box 8)
- T-Shirts
  - Levine Huntley Schmidt and Beaver, Inc. Make the Logo Smaller and the Idea Bigger. Undated. (Box 9)
  - Morris the Cat. Undated. (Box 9)
  - Morris the Cat for President. 1988. (Box 9)
- Audiovisual Materials
  - 28th International Broadcasting Awards: World's Best Radio Commercials. 1987. Audiocassette. (Box 10)
  - 29th International Broadcasting Awards: World's Best Radio Commercials. 1988. Audiocassette. (Box 10)
  - 30th International Broadcasting Awards: World's Best Radio Commercials Plus Best of Three Decades. 1989. Audiocassette. (Box 10)
  - 50 Old Time Radio Commercials. 1978. Audiocassette. (Box 10)
  - Fundamentals of Retail Newspaper Advertising. Fairchild Publications. 1979.Audiocassette. (Box 10)
  - J.C. Penney Consumer Affairs Forum: Regulation and Regulatory Reform Implications and Impact. 1976. Audiocassette. (Box 10)
  - Labov & Beyond Sample #17. Undated. Audiocassette. (Box 10)
  - Labov & Beyond Sample #18. Undated. Audiocassette. (Box 10)
  - NPR Marketplace Advertising. 1991. Audiocassette. (Box 10)
  - Radio Advertising Bureau: Auto Dealers. 1985. Audiocassette. (Box 10)
  - Radio Advertising Bureau: Furniture Dealers. 1985. Audiocassette. (Box 10)
  - Radio Advertising Bureau: Hospitals FSEC. 1985. Audiocassette. (Box 10)
  - Radio Advertising Bureau: Movie Theatres. 1985. Audiocassette. (Box 10)
  - Radio Advertising Bureau: Workshop Highlights. 1985. Audiocassette. (Box 10)
  - Radio Advertising Bureau. Serial Cassettes for Manager's and Sales Meeting Use. 1986. Tapes 1-10, 12. Audiocassette. (Box 10)
  - Radio Advertising Bureau. Serial Cassettes for Manager's and Sales Meeting Use. 1987. Tapes 1-5, 7-12. Audiocassette. (Box 10)
  - Radio Advertising Bureau. Serial Cassettes for Manager's and Sales Meeting Use. 1988. Tapes 1-7, 9-12. Audiocassette. (Box 10)
  - Radio Advertising Bureau. Serial Cassettes for Manager's and Sales Meeting Use. 1989. Tapes 1-12. Audiocassette. (Box 10)
  - Radio Advertising Bureau. Serial Cassettes for Manager's and Sales Meeting Use. 1990. Tapes 3-5. Audiocassette. (Box 10)
  - Dancer fitzgerald Sample: de Haviland. 1976. 16mm. (Box 10)
  - McCann-Erickson Coca-Cola Campaigns. Undated. 16mm. (Box 10)
  - Untitled. Undated. 16mm. (Box 10)
  - Bert, Barz & Kirby: Our Representative Smattering of the Things We Do in the Way of Creative Radio Spots. Undated. Audio reel. (Box 10)
  - Radio Advertising Bureau: I Saw It on the Radio campaign spots. 1986-1987. Audio reel. (Box 10)
  - Radio Advertising Bureau: I Saw It on the Radio campaign spots. 1987-1988. Audio reel. (Box 10)